<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<data>
	<node>
		<name><![CDATA[The False Economy of Cheap Gear]]></name>
		<slug><![CDATA[false-economy-of-cheap-gear]]></slug>
		<collectionid><![CDATA[5c684cb846b367f341f2e361]]></collectionid>
		<itemid><![CDATA[5c684cb846b367a49bf2e4c2]]></itemid>
		<createdon><![CDATA[Wed Nov 16 2016 13:25:28 GMT+0000 (Coordinated Universal Time)]]></createdon>
		<updatedon><![CDATA[Wed Jul 03 2024 21:13:39 GMT+0000 (Coordinated Universal Time)]]></updatedon>
		<publishedon><![CDATA[Wed Jul 03 2024 21:52:06 GMT+0000 (Coordinated Universal Time)]]></publishedon>
		<summary><![CDATA[Anglers new to saltwater fly fishing will learn faster and save money in the long run by investing in quality gear. ]]></summary>
		<body><![CDATA[<p id="">When you are new to saltwater fly fishing, the question of what rod and reel to purchase is one of the first important decisions you'll make. Unfortunately, many saltwater fly fishing novices believe going cheap is rational because they have yet to determine if they like the sport or will stick with it. &nbsp;Those new to this sport should try to understand that saltwater fly fishing is not a rational sport! &nbsp;Who travels thousands of miles to distant parts of the world and spends endless hours pursuing fish that are difficult to see and even harder to catch? The Saltwater Flyfisher. </p><p id="">We are not suggesting that you spend money needlessly, but take a step back and look at the saltwater gear options available today. There are many available choices of rods, reels, lines, and other equipment, and the possibilities keep growing. A fundamental concept to remember is that the right stuff is a lot easier to learn with than many of the budget options. The learning phase can be considerably longer if you go the less-expensive route. &nbsp;</p><p id="">Saltwater fly fishing puts extreme demands on gear, and the better gear performs much better, making your initiation more rewarding and fulfilling. Buying less expensive equipment can work, but given the time you have to learn, the better gear will get you there much faster. We recommend buying the best equipment you can afford without missing a mortgage or tuition payments. You will learn quicker and have more fun. Also important to remember is that most premium gear carries a lifetime guarantee. If you have access to a local fly fishing shop, they may rent premium gear so you can fish with it before deciding to buy. See our Fishing Gear for Belize page for gear guidelines and recommendations. Those of us addicted to this crazy sport will tell you that you can never have too much gear, but if you're starting out and would like more insight, feel free to contact us for more information.</p><p id="">‍</p>]]></body>
		<metadescription><![CDATA[New to saltwater fly fishing? Invest in quality gear to make learning easier and more rewarding. Discover our gear recommendations for Belize fishing. Contact u]]></metadescription>
	</node>
	<node>
		<name><![CDATA[Fly Fishing from a Kayak]]></name>
		<slug><![CDATA[fly-fishing-from-a-kayak]]></slug>
		<collectionid><![CDATA[5c684cb846b367f341f2e361]]></collectionid>
		<itemid><![CDATA[5c684cb846b367509cf2e3f0]]></itemid>
		<createdon><![CDATA[Wed Nov 16 2016 12:32:57 GMT+0000 (Coordinated Universal Time)]]></createdon>
		<updatedon><![CDATA[Wed Jul 03 2024 21:15:49 GMT+0000 (Coordinated Universal Time)]]></updatedon>
		<publishedon><![CDATA[Wed Jul 03 2024 21:52:06 GMT+0000 (Coordinated Universal Time)]]></publishedon>
		<summary><![CDATA[Rarely fished flats behind Ambergris Caye offer the kayaker incredible opportunities for large bones. Miles of water is accessible and our kayaks are complimentary for guests.]]></summary>
		<body><![CDATA[<p>Fly Fishing from a kayak in Belize or bird watching in the lagoons around Ambergris Caye is a fun way to spend a morning or afternoon.</p><p>El Pescador has, in addition to 200 square miles of flats fishing heaven, a small fleet of kayaks for your use. If you have an adventurous spirit, you can use our complimentary kayaks to explore the many lagoons and flats behind our lodge. Many of these rarely fished flats have some very nice bonefish and yes even the occasional permit, and you can have at them at your convenience.</p><h3>Explore the flats of Ambergris Caye</h3><p>What you need is to allow enough time to explore these flats at least 3 or 4 hours will allow you to begin finding fish on the predominantly white sand flats that extend virtually all the way to Mexico. It takes some time to learn your way through and around the mangroves that are home to bones and countless numbers of wading birds. I often see a dozen or more varieties of birds while spending the day fishing these flats. Some flats are sand, some turtle grass and some are limestone mud. These mud flats you DO NOT want to wade. Always check the firmness with your paddle before you get out of the kayak to assure that the bottom is firm.</p><h3>Fly Fishing Gear</h3><p>In terms of gear, you'll need a 7, 8 or 9 weight, floating line and a small selection of Gotchas, Charlies, and Christmas Island Specials, and make sure you have a few weedless patterns for the turtle grass. We'll put you into the water on one of our kayaks (all are sit-on-tops) and make sure you have water, lunch if you're going out for the day, plenty of sunscreen and some basic directions to help you begin to explore the wonderful experience of exploring by yourself. This is a unique offering you'll not find often, and the only cost to you is the time needed to begin the exploration of your flats fishing independence.</p>]]></body>
		<metadescription><![CDATA[Explore Ambergris Caye by kayak at El Pescador. Enjoy fly fishing for bonefish and permit or bird watching in the lagoons. Complimentary kayaks available now!]]></metadescription>
	</node>
	<node>
		<name><![CDATA[Keep Stripping]]></name>
		<slug><![CDATA[keep-stripping]]></slug>
		<collectionid><![CDATA[5c684cb846b367f341f2e361]]></collectionid>
		<itemid><![CDATA[5c684cb846b367c756f2e478]]></itemid>
		<createdon><![CDATA[Wed Nov 16 2016 12:27:13 GMT+0000 (Coordinated Universal Time)]]></createdon>
		<updatedon><![CDATA[Wed Jul 03 2024 21:17:40 GMT+0000 (Coordinated Universal Time)]]></updatedon>
		<publishedon><![CDATA[Wed Jul 03 2024 21:52:06 GMT+0000 (Coordinated Universal Time)]]></publishedon>
		<summary><![CDATA[Do not give up on a cast, especially in cloudy water or under any circumstances where visibility is limited.]]></summary>
		<body><![CDATA[<p id="">No, we're not talking about removing your clothes. Having spent literally thousands of hours on the flats, I have learned that often, just when I'm about to give up and cast again to another fish, a fish eats my fly right next to the boat. Why this is so is a subject of some debate, but the fact remains that a fish we see and cast to at 80 or 90 feet magically seems to disappear, and then right at the boat he eats.</p><p id="">The moral of this story is quite simple: do not give up on a cast, especially in cloudy water or under any circumstances where visibility is limited. Often, the bottom of the flats and the fish are the same color, making it difficult and sometimes impossible to tell them apart. Under these conditions, keep stripping until you run out of fly line (you do not want to bring the last of the fly line inside your rod tip) and you might be rewarded. One of the most frequent things your guide will say to you during a day on the flats will probably be "KEEP STRIPPING!!!"</p>]]></body>
		<metadescription><![CDATA[Don't give up on your cast while fly fishing at El Pescador. Fish often strike close to the boat. Keep stripping, especially in cloudy waters!]]></metadescription>
	</node>
	<node>
		<name><![CDATA[Make Your Cast Count]]></name>
		<slug><![CDATA[make-your-cast-count]]></slug>
		<collectionid><![CDATA[5c684cb846b367f341f2e361]]></collectionid>
		<itemid><![CDATA[5c684cb846b367246cf2e49e]]></itemid>
		<createdon><![CDATA[Wed Nov 16 2016 12:52:14 GMT+0000 (Coordinated Universal Time)]]></createdon>
		<updatedon><![CDATA[Wed Jul 03 2024 21:09:29 GMT+0000 (Coordinated Universal Time)]]></updatedon>
		<publishedon><![CDATA[Wed Jul 03 2024 21:52:06 GMT+0000 (Coordinated Universal Time)]]></publishedon>
		<summary><![CDATA[Over many years of saltwater flats fishing, a few major lessons creep into one's consciousness. Perhaps the very most important, at least in this writer's experience, is simply this: MAKE THE FIRST CAST COUNT.]]></summary>
		<body><![CDATA[<p>Over many years of saltwater flats fishing, a few major lessons creep into one's consciousness. Perhaps the very most important, at least in this writer's experience, is simply this: MAKE THE FIRST CAST COUNT.</p><p>In a fishery as diverse and bountiful as the one here at El Pescador, it is easy, very easy to get lulled into a false sense of security. What I mean is that it is okay to expect to get dozens, even hundreds of shots during a day of bonefishing, multiple shots at tarpon and permit. Knowing that you may have many shots, &nbsp;why &nbsp;is it important to &nbsp;"make the first cast count?" &nbsp;You just never know when the next fish may be a 100-pound tarpon, a 20-pound permit or a 6-pound bonefish. As a result, it never pays to relax when you are on the bow of the boat looking for fish. The next fish you see may be the fish of a lifetime -- so let's be ready.</p><p>When this fish shows itself to you, the very best chance you will have is the very first cast. This cast gives you the opportunity to surprise the fish. By the second or third cast, your fish of a lifetime begins to get the sense that something's amiss, and you may blow your chance. Practice making the first cast count in your backyard. One or two false casts and hit your spot.</p><p>"Make the first cast count" is a very useful mantra to have as you board the flats boats on the dock each morning. Use it and live it and enjoy the great fulfillment of realizing those dreams of landing the big one, rather than talking about the one that got away.</p>]]></body>
		<metadescription><![CDATA[Maximize your success at El Pescador's bountiful fishery by making the first cast count. Practice your cast and be ready for the fish of a lifetime. Book today!]]></metadescription>
	</node>
	<node>
		<name><![CDATA[Realistic Expectations while Fishing]]></name>
		<slug><![CDATA[realistic-expectations-while-fishing]]></slug>
		<collectionid><![CDATA[5c684cb846b367f341f2e361]]></collectionid>
		<itemid><![CDATA[5c684cb846b3675385f2e48b]]></itemid>
		<createdon><![CDATA[Wed Nov 16 2016 12:42:47 GMT+0000 (Coordinated Universal Time)]]></createdon>
		<updatedon><![CDATA[Wed Jul 03 2024 21:15:13 GMT+0000 (Coordinated Universal Time)]]></updatedon>
		<publishedon><![CDATA[Wed Jul 03 2024 21:52:06 GMT+0000 (Coordinated Universal Time)]]></publishedon>
		<summary><![CDATA[We have over 200 square miles of flats fishing and an abundant and diverse fishery. So what should your expectations be?]]></summary>
		<body><![CDATA[<p id="">At El Pescador in Ambergris Caye, Belize, we have over 200 square miles of flats fishing and an abundant and diverse fishery. So, what should your expectations be?</p><p id="">While this area is one of the largest yet lightly fished, don't be lulled into thinking it's easy. We have days where the bones, permit, tarpon, and jacks are cooperative, but fishing the flats is more of a hunting experience than one where you catch dozens of fish each day.</p><p id="">The best word to describe this fishery is challenging. It's not impossible, but the fish here tend to reward good casts and avoid poor ones.</p><p id="">We have miles of beautiful flats where bonefish swim in very shallow water. Fish in shallow water are more demanding since they are acutely aware of anything abnormal. Lengthening your leaders, using lightweight flies, and casting accurately is essential.</p><p id="">Most of our flats are in shallow water, meaning you'll often throw to tarpon in 2 or 3 feet of water. When a tarpon nails your fly in shallow water, it's an unforgettable experience. So, while the fishery can be easy and challenging at times, one word to describe the Belize fishery is rewarding.</p>]]></body>
		<metadescription><![CDATA[Experience the rewarding challenge of flats fishing at El Pescador in Ambergris Caye, Belize. With 200 square miles of diverse flats, prepare for an unforgettab]]></metadescription>
	</node>
	<node>
		<name><![CDATA[Saltwater Spin Fishing at El Pescador]]></name>
		<slug><![CDATA[saltwater-spin-fishing-at-el-pescador]]></slug>
		<collectionid><![CDATA[5c684cb846b367f341f2e361]]></collectionid>
		<itemid><![CDATA[5c684cb846b367498df2e38c]]></itemid>
		<createdon><![CDATA[Wed Nov 16 2016 13:28:28 GMT+0000 (Coordinated Universal Time)]]></createdon>
		<updatedon><![CDATA[Wed Jul 03 2024 21:08:51 GMT+0000 (Coordinated Universal Time)]]></updatedon>
		<publishedon><![CDATA[Wed Jul 03 2024 21:52:06 GMT+0000 (Coordinated Universal Time)]]></publishedon>
		<summary><![CDATA[El Pescador resort in Ambergris Caye, Belize is known worldwide as one of the finest saltwater flats fisheries anywhere. The incredible opportunities presented by this fishery apply as much to the spin fisher as the fly fisher.]]></summary>
		<body><![CDATA[<p>El Pescador in Ambergris Caye, Belize is known worldwide as one of the finest saltwater flats fisheries anywhere. The incredible fishing opportunities here apply as much to the spin fisher as the fly fisher.</p><p>We have close to 400 square miles of flats ranging in depth from less than a foot to 15-20 feet. We also have the second longest coral reef in the world less than a thousand yards from the lodge. On many days, anglers trolling along this reef land some huge barracuda as well as a variety of other species.</p><p>For those spin fishing anglers who may at first shy away from a fly fishing destination, please reconsider. As many as 25% of our guests avail themselves of this amazingly diverse and abundant fishery with spin or conventional gear. If you plan to use your spin gear, the list of what to bring is very simple.</p><p>Bring a 10 lb- 12 lb. outfit for bones, permit and the like.</p><p>Bring a 20 lb. - 25 lb. set up for tarpon, jacks and barracuda.</p><p>We use small (1/8 to 1/4 ounce) jigs with shrimp for the smaller species. For the tarpon, barracuda and large jacks, we like to live line sardines, so bring some 3/0 circle hooks for the big boys.</p><p>One of our spin fishing guests recently set a new lodge record after landing 15 big jacks (12-18 lbs) using sardines as well as a few of his favorite plugs, all in a single day!</p><p>We do maintain a small number of spin rigs here, but it is far better to bring your gear. You're familiar with it, and this way you can be sure you have what you need to enjoy spin fishing in one of the premier saltwater flats fisheries on earth.</p>]]></body>
		<metadescription><![CDATA[El Pescador in Ambergris Caye, Belize, offers world-class fishing for both spin and fly fishers. Explore 400 square miles of flats fishing paradise. Explore now]]></metadescription>
	</node>
	<node>
		<name><![CDATA[Selecting Saltwater Fly Lines]]></name>
		<slug><![CDATA[selecting-saltwater-fly-lines]]></slug>
		<collectionid><![CDATA[5c684cb846b367f341f2e361]]></collectionid>
		<itemid><![CDATA[5c684cb846b367b830f2e4b0]]></itemid>
		<createdon><![CDATA[Wed Nov 16 2016 12:58:57 GMT+0000 (Coordinated Universal Time)]]></createdon>
		<updatedon><![CDATA[Wed Jul 03 2024 20:47:39 GMT+0000 (Coordinated Universal Time)]]></updatedon>
		<publishedon><![CDATA[Wed Jul 03 2024 21:52:06 GMT+0000 (Coordinated Universal Time)]]></publishedon>
		<summary><![CDATA[Saltwater fish are always on the move and you probably have just one cast to a given fish. Increase your odds by selecting a line that will quickly deliver the fly with a minimum of false casts.]]></summary>
		<body><![CDATA[<p id="">We are always a bit mystified when we see guests spend $600 or $700 on a new fly rod, $500 on a new reel, and then buy only one fly line.</p><p id="">Finding the right fly line for your rod is like the purchase of a tuner for a guitar -- so let's try to tune your rod. There is no way to effectively do this without trying several lines to find out which ones you prefer, and which ones feel right. Go to your local shop and try a few. Then spend another 50 or 60 bucks to make your rod "sing" when you cast. You''ll have more fun, probably catch more fish, and all for spending an extra $50 after you just laid down as much as fifteen hundred for that new outfit!</p><p id="">While there are a growing number of saltwater fly lines on the market, there are some basic guidelines to help you make an intelligent selection without being brand specific.</p><p id="">The most critical characteristic is that the line is an aggressive, front-loaded taper to deliver the fly accurately and QUICKLY to the fish.</p><p id="">Unlike many freshwater species that may live and eat in a particular spot for an entire season, saltwater species are almost always on the move. Once your guide tells you where to cast, you have seconds (not 30 or 40 seconds, but more like 7, 8 or 10 if you're lucky!) to deliver the fly. As a result, you need a line that will deliver the fly with a minimum of false casts in the shortest time.</p><p id="">Assume that while saltwater fly fishing, you are going to get only one cast to a given fish, which is usually true. The way to make that first cast count is by testing a variety and selecting the best fly line for the rod and conditions you're fishing.</p><p id="">If you are interested in specific local favorites, contact us and we'll be happy to provide you with a list of our go-to fly lines.</p>]]></body>
		<metadescription><![CDATA[Maximize your chances in saltwater fishing with the right fly line. Learn tips for quick, accurate casts on Ambergris Caye, Belize. Explore more now!]]></metadescription>
	</node>
	<node>
		<name><![CDATA[Tarpon Flies]]></name>
		<slug><![CDATA[tarpon-flies]]></slug>
		<collectionid><![CDATA[5c684cb846b367f341f2e361]]></collectionid>
		<itemid><![CDATA[5c684cb846b3677f06f2e3dc]]></itemid>
		<createdon><![CDATA[Wed Nov 16 2016 12:19:25 GMT+0000 (Coordinated Universal Time)]]></createdon>
		<updatedon><![CDATA[Wed Jul 03 2024 20:19:23 GMT+0000 (Coordinated Universal Time)]]></updatedon>
		<publishedon><![CDATA[Wed Jul 03 2024 21:52:06 GMT+0000 (Coordinated Universal Time)]]></publishedon>
		<summary><![CDATA[The "Black Death" tarpon fly is one of the most productive here in Belize. There are times and locations, however, where other flies will do the job and sometimes do it better.]]></summary>
		<body><![CDATA[<p>The "Black Death" tarpon fly is one of the most productive here in Belize. There are times and locations, however, where other flies will do the job and sometimes do it better.</p><p>The Black Death fly pattern accounts for many of the tarpon we land, and while this is a very productive fly, there are times and locations, where other flies will do the job and sometimes do it better.</p><p>Sometimes lighter patterns work better than Black Death's. So you should have a selection.</p><p>On many of our tarpon flats the bottom is white sand, and in this environment, the lighter flies tend to be my personal favorites. Patterns like the Green Hornet, Sardine ( Sardinia ) and the White Angel are great producers. If you are tying your own, you want to make sure you include plenty of tinsel flash. The flash seems to be of primary importance. Often this fly seems to be more visible to the fish, and they frequently seem to 'see' it out of the corner of their eye and will often change direction to eat.</p><p>Another consideration is hook size. While we usually use 3/0 or 4/0 hooks on the Black Death patterns, I have found excellent success with 1/0 hooks for these lighter patterns with flash. With a smaller hook, you can cast farther. Many times you get only one shot at a fish, especially if it's moving away and that extra 10, 15, or 20 feet can make the difference between the fish 'seeing the flash' and not seeing it resulting in either success or failure.</p><p>While the subject of hooks ( J versus Circle ), the choice is yours. There are advocates of each, and you should use the hook that instills the most confidence.</p><p>Leverage your guides knowledge on the water. Their experience in our local waters is unmatched.</p>]]></body>
		<metadescription><![CDATA[Learn about the "Black Death" tarpon fly and other effective flies for fishing in Belize. Get tips for the best fishing spots on Ambergris Caye. Explore now!]]></metadescription>
	</node>
	<node>
		<name><![CDATA[Ten Tips to Enhance Your Fishing Trip]]></name>
		<slug><![CDATA[ten-tips-to-enhance-your-fishing-trip]]></slug>
		<collectionid><![CDATA[5c684cb846b367f341f2e361]]></collectionid>
		<itemid><![CDATA[5c684cb846b3671101f2e4d4]]></itemid>
		<createdon><![CDATA[Wed Nov 16 2016 13:33:22 GMT+0000 (Coordinated Universal Time)]]></createdon>
		<updatedon><![CDATA[Wed Jul 03 2024 21:07:45 GMT+0000 (Coordinated Universal Time)]]></updatedon>
		<publishedon><![CDATA[Wed Jul 03 2024 21:52:06 GMT+0000 (Coordinated Universal Time)]]></publishedon>
		<summary><![CDATA[Here are ten things you can do to enhance your salt water flats guided fishing at El Pescador.]]></summary>
		<body><![CDATA[<p>1. Prepare for your trip. If you are fly fishing, practice for five minutes a few times a week before your trip. If you are new to fly fishing, try to take a casting lesson before your trip at your local fly shop.  If you are spin fishing, make sure you are fishing the tackle you want for your experience. </p><p>2. Trust that El Pescador Lodge is a premier fishing lodge. Our guides know the water and have been with El Pescador for many years, some for over 30 years. Ask the guide in the morning about the fishing. Do you want to bonefish all day? Is there a chance for permit or tarpon? Are you interested in different species? It is not productive to arrive and tell the guide how to perform his duties. </p><p>3. Realistic expectations. If a grand slam happened all the time, it wouldn't be special. One goal might be to leave the lodge a better angler. </p><p>4. Control what you can. Bring your polarized glasses, rain gear, sunscreen (remember to check the expiration date). Bring all of your fishing tackle. Drink a lot of water on the boat. If you like to have your cocktails, you will want to make sure you drink even more water. Check the cooler on the boat with your lunch. It is straightforward to make changes while still on the dock, but somewhat tricky once you are on the flats. </p><p>5. Show your guide your cast first thing. Let the guide know your goals. Our guides love to cast and will be happy to help you with your cast. We also offer complimentary casting lessons each afternoon. Please take advantage of this excellent service to maximize your fishing day with the guide. We offer casting instruction for all experience levels. Please schedule a lesson with the Front Desk. </p><p>6. Communicate throughout the day. Talk with your guide. If you want to see if there is something else to do, ask. Some anglers prefer to wade fish, just ask the guide for this opportunity. If you are tarpon fishing and you need a tug desperately, see if you can go catch a bonefish.</p><p>7. If you are fishing with a large group, don't plan on meeting up for lunch, unless you plan on a shore lunch. Group lunches mean guides have to change their fishing game plans to rendezvous at the same time and location. This hurts your fishing in the end. Our shore lunch is terrific, and is a good time for families and groups to spend time together. However, it is not a productive use of your fishing day. If you want to capitalize on your fishing opportunities, order a boxed lunch which may be consumed as you wish throughout the day. </p><p>8. Tipping. Is a personal decision based on service. See our <a href="/lodge/faq" data-rt-link-type="page" data-rt-link-pageid="5beb08a85af27bc69e98ef56">FAQ page</a> for tip recommendations. </p><p>9. Hook and cook. Bonefish, permit, and tarpon are all catch and release in Belize. If you catch snapper, grouper, jack, etc., we are happy to prepare this for you at the lodge in addition to our regular dinner menu (at no additional charge). Please take no more than you will personally eat and release the rest. Guides love to take home fish, so make sure to tell them if you wish for them to have the fish or if you prefer they clean the fish for you and leave it with you. </p><p>10. Have fun. It is our mission to make sure you have everything you need for a safe and fun fishing experience. We are an extended family and hope that you feel like part of our family when you leave. Sharing time and adventures with family and friends is the best fun we know!</p><p>‍</p>]]></body>
		<metadescription><![CDATA[Prepare for a successful fishing trip at El Pescador Lodge with these tips. Practice casting, communicate with guides, and enjoy the adventure. Book now!]]></metadescription>
	</node>
</data>
